Guide to the Jack Wolf Collection ARS.0088
Archive of Recorded Sound
Jack Wolf Collection
1960-2004
ARS.0088
Wolf, Jack
3 boxes: One hundred seventy-three (173) audiocassettes; forty-five (45) open reel tapes
Archive of Recorded Sound
Field recordings of environmental sounds from around the world, captured by hobbyist Jack Wolf.
Access
Open for research; material must be requested at least two business days in advance of intended use. Contact the Archive for assistance.
Source
The Jack Wolf Collection was donated to the Stanford Archive of Recorded Sound by Judy Wolf Cannady in 2007.
Scope and Contents
Jack Wolf, who often referred to himself as "Bwana Jack," lived alone in Marina Del Ray, California until he passed away from cancer circa 2006. A Stanford graduate, Wolf was a banker by trade, as well as a world traveler, naturalist and animal lover. Beginning in the late 1960s, he began recording environmental sounds on his excursions abroad, mostly for his own enjoyment. Wolf collected sounds from Africa, Asia (particularly the South Pacific islands), Amazon, Costa Rica, and the United States.
In a memo Wolf wrote in 1992, he explained what motivated him: "they are by and large natural sounds, birds and animals, collected as a hobby and as a 'sound bank' for future generations so that they know what the world sounded like in the still-wild late 20th century." Through the 1990s, his tapes chronicle the encroachment of once-remote locales by motor noise, international jet travel, domesticated animals, and, of course, other people. Although an admitted amateur, he was proud to note that the Los Angeles Museum of Natural History used his recordings of Amazonian birdcalls. He also made a series of Amazon trips with UCLA professor Mildred Mathias. Wolf expressed a hope that his collection would someday be deposited in an archive.
The majority of tapes are from Sumatra, Borneo, and Malaysia, places Wolf returned to frequently. He also made many recordings in Tanzania and Kenya. However, he was not averse to exploring some of the more remote areas of the Western United States, including Montana, Arizona, New Mexico, Washington, Utah, Nevada, and California's Anza-Borreaga Desert. In his recordings, Wolf used a Sony portable recorder and Sennheiser microphones. He reviewed his work closely, edited tapes, and put his favorite recordings on special reels. Although there's little mention of the recordings, a chronology and other contextual information may be gleaned from copies of his annual Christmas letters from 1968 to 2004, included with the collection. There are many pages of personal notes about the tapes, though, and specific animals are sometimes identified.
Animals, especially insects, primates, and birds, are foregrounded, but the sounds of weather (wind, rain, thunder) and waterfalls are also prevalent. In the Amazon, Wolf wrote of "good rain storms," "night crickets...just dripping canopy...quacks on landing dock," and "frogs and dogs and drums...too many dogs!" Evocative descriptions of these moments continue in Costa Rica ("Toucans and mosquitos...Howlers, then hum of boat or car..."), and Africa ("Bird and cricket, mostly cricket," "Flamingos at night...emerald spotted wood dove," "Baboons grunting and barking," "Herd of zebra through camp, good sound," "Bush babies, woke me up!," "Snapping fire and birds," "Morning birds and dew dropping on tent," "Very close hyena," "Hyena growl at lion kill," "Hippo on the Mara.") On one trip to Kenya in 1991, Wolf "left the recorder going for one hour each day at remote Mukatan sites. Hiked while recording was going on, so no people, no cattle. Just the pure Mukatan-my favorite Earth spot." Of course, Wolf's mics also captured the sounds of his own presence: his campfire, his guides, conversations among companions, so much that some tapes could almost be called "Sounds of Men Camping." But there are many hours of undisturbed nature here, and from places where that might not be possible even ten years later.
Indexing Terms
Field recordings; Nature sounds
- Cassettes - Original Recordings
  - Cassette Box 1 [notes enclosed], 1981-1984 (Audio 1, Box 1)
    Scope and Contents
    Costa Rica 1981; Amazon 1982; Borneo 1983; Amazon 1984
  - Cassette Box 2 [notes enclosed], 1973-1994 (Audio 1, Box 2)
    Africa 1973; Africa 1974; Africa September 1991
  - Cassette Box 3 [notes enclosed] (Audio 1, Box 3)
    Kenya, Tanzania 1975; Africa 1976; Africa 1978; Anza 1991-1992
  - Cassette Box 4 [notes enclosed], 1979-1989 (Audio 3, Box 4)
    Amazon 1979; Amazon 1980; Amazon 1985; Amazon 1990; Montana 1988; Arizona, New Mexico 1989
  - Cassette Box 5 [notes enclosed], 1973-1991 (Audio 3, Box 5)
    Africa 1977; Best Quiet Sounds Master 1 and 2; Best American Tropics; Africa Quiet Moods 1973-1976 I-III; Africa 1978; Africa 1991; Mkutano Gorge, Kenya 1991; Best of Africa 1973-1991; Costa Rica Dec. 1979; Anza September 1993; Washington State June 1991
  - Cassette Box 6 [notes enclosed], 1981-1991 (Audio 3, Box 6)
    Angelina Springs March 1990; Organ Pipe National Monument April 1989; Amazon Quiet Moods, Rain 1984-1985; U.S. Birds - Mountain and Desert; Okefanokee Swamp (from Beanie, Region II Xmas Party 1983); Fishlake National Forest, Utah 6/5/91; Mile High, Arizona 4/81; Jungle Rain 1990
- Open Reel Tapes [Notes Enclosed]
  - A. Sumatra - Borneo - Malaysia 1983; 1984 Amazon, 1 7" open reel tape (Audio 2)
  - B. Sounds of the Amazon and Costa Rica 1979; Amazon 1980, 1979-1980; 1 7" open reel tape (Audio 2)
  - C. Amazon 1980, 1 7" open reel tape (Audio 2)
  - D. Amazon 1984 End; Amazon 1985, 1987; Amazon 1990 Start, 1984-1990; 1 7" open reel tape (Audio 2)
  - E. Amazon 1990, 1 7" open reel tape (Audio 2)
  - F. Amazon Quiet Tape, 1990; 1 7" open reel tape (Audio 2)
  - G. Costa Rica 1981 part I, 1 7" open reel tape (Audio 2)
  - H. Costa Rica 1981 part II; Amazon 1982, 1981-1982; 1 7" open reel tape (Audio 2)
  - I. Domestic Birds, 1988-1991; 1 7" open reel tape (Audio 2)
    Scope and Contents note
    Montana, Idaho 1988; Arizona 1989; Nebraska 1989; Angelina Springs 1990-1991. Side two mostly desert sounds (organ pipe, Anza)
  - J. Domestic Birds #2, 1988-1991; 1 7" open reel tape (Audio 2)
    Anza Desert 1991-1993; Northeast Washington and Utah 1991
  - I. Africa - Songs and Animals, 1972; 1 7" open reel tape (Audio 2)
  - II. Africa [Kenya] - Best of '72, 1972-10; 1 7" open reel tape (Audio 2)
  - III-V. Africa II, 1973; 3 7" open reel tapes (Audio 2)
  - VI. Africa 1974-1975, 1 7" open reel tape (Audio 2)
  - VII. Africa [Kenya and Tanzania] 1974, 1 7" open reel tape (Audio 2)
  - VIII. Africa 1975-1976, 1 7" open reel tape (Audio 2)
  - IX-X. Africa 1977 [Kenya], 2 7" open reel tapes (Audio 2)
  - XI. Africa 1978, 1 7" open reel tape (Audio 2)
  - XII. Africa 1978, 1991, 1 7" open reel tape (Audio 2)
  - XIII. Africa 1991, 1 7" open reel tape (Audio 2)
  - XIV. Best of Africa, 1973-1978; 1 7" open reel tape (Audio 2)
  - Best of Tahiti, 1 7" open reel tape (Audio 2)
  - Tahiti, 29th Birthday, 1960-11-11; 1 5" open reel tape (Audio 2)
  - Tahiti #1; Reflections and Return to Tahiti; Random Thoughts, 4 3" open reel tapes (Audio 2)
  - Tahiti - Samoa Originals, 5 3" open reel tapes (Audio 2)
  - Micronesia Oct. 1970; Hawaii; Monologue May '69, etc., 1969-1970; 5 3" open reel tapes (Audio 2)
  - Africa, 1972; 6 5" open reel tapes (Audio 2)